this video is all about gravitational
acceleration
and how to calculate it
so let's start with this example
calculate the acceleration due to
gravity on the moon
which has a mass of 7.35
times 10 to the 22 kilograms
and a radius
of 1.74 times 10 to the 6 meters
so what formula can we use to calculate
the acceleration due to gravity
of a planetary body
well let's draw a picture
so let's say this is the moon
and we have some object
that's to the left of the moon
now the moon
is going to pull the object toward
itself
and so this object is going to have an
acceleration
imagine if you have an apple
and you let the apple go it's going to
fall to the ground the earth is going to
pull the apple toward itself
so the same is true with the moon
the moon the moon is going to exert a
gravitational force that's going to take
this object and pull it towards the moon
and so that object has an acceleration
and that acceleration is known as the
acceleration due to gravity so we want
to calculate it
so let's write an expression for the net
force in the x direction
the only force that's acting on this
object is the force of gravity
now the moon pulls on this object with a
force f and that object pulls
on the moon with the same force
so let's just call that force fg force
of gravity
now the net force according to newton's
second law
is mass
times acceleration
now let's say lowercase m is the mass of
the object capital m is the mass of the
moon
the gravitational force
is equal
to the gravitational constant
times the two masses the mass of the
object and the mass of the moon divided
by the square of the distance between
them where r is the distance between the
center of the object and the center of
the moon
now the next thing that we could do is
we can cancel the mass of the object
and so the acceleration in the x
direction is g
m over r squared
the acceleration due to gravity
you've probably seen it as lowercase g
so lowercase g for any
planet or moon is going to be the
universal gravitational constant
times the mass of that planet divided by
the square of the distance
so this is the form that you need to
calculate the gravitational acceleration
so let's go ahead and finish this
problem
the universal gravitational constant
is 6.67
times 10 to the minus 11.
the mass of the moon is given to us
and so that's 7.35
times 10 to the 22 kilograms
and the distance
between
the object and the moon
is really the radius of the moon we want
to find the acceleration due to gravity
our moon
so let's assume that the object is
actually
on the surface of the moon
i drew it over here just to
draw this
just to come up with the equations
that's going to help us to derive this
equation
but we want to find the acceleration due
to gravity on the moon so technically
the object should be on it which means
the distance
between the object and the center of the
moon
is just the radius
of the moon so r is going to be 1.74
times 10 to the sixth
and don't forget to square it
otherwise you won't get the right answer
that's a very common mistake
so the gravitational acceleration on the
moon
based on this information is about 1.62
meters per second squared
and that's it
now let's move on to this problem
calculate the acceleration due to
gravity on the surface of the earth
and 3 500 kilometers above the surface
of the earth
and we're given the mass of the earth
and the radius of the earth
all right so let's start with the center
i'm not the center but the surface of
the earth
so what is the acceleration at let's say
point a
on the surface of the earth so we're
going to use this equation
gm
over r squared
so capital g is going to be the same
it's a constant it's not going to change
the mass of the earth that's 5.97
times 10 to the 24 kilograms
and the radius of the earth is 6.38
times 10 to the 6 meters
and we're going to square it
so the gravitational acceleration
is 9.78
meters per second squared
which
you could round it and say
it's about 9.8 so that's how you can
calculate the gravitational acceleration
of the earth
using that formula
now
when an object moves further away from
the earth the gravitational acceleration
decreases
because it's inversely related to the
square of the distance so as the
distance from the earth increases the
gravitational acceleration uh decreases
so let's calculate
the acceleration due to gravity
for an object that's 3 500 kilometers
above the surface of the earth
so it's going to be less than 9.78 let's
see
how much less it's going to be
so let's say that object is located at
point b
so the distance between the surface of
the earth
and that object
is 3 500 kilometers
so now let's use the formula
g is equal to gm
over r squared
capital g is the same
and the mass of the earth
that's constant that's not going to
change either
now what's r in this problem
r is the distance between the center of
the earth and point b
so keep in mind the radius of the earth
we have that
i'm going to write it as r but it's 6.38
times 10 to the sixth
so let me draw the picture
i need to draw a bigger picture let's
say this is the earth
so this distance here that's 6.38
times 10 to the sixth
and then we have this distance between
the surface of the earth and point b
that's
3 500 kilometers and one kilometer
is a thousand meters so if we convert it
we need to multiply
3 500 kilometers by thousands to convert
it to meters
so 3 500 times a thousand
is 3.5 million
which is 3.5 times 10 to the 6 meters
so before you add these two
make sure that the unit is the same
because the radius is in meters so that
has to be meters as well
so therefore r
is the total distance from the center of
the earth to point b so we need to add
these two numbers if you missed a step
you will not get the right answer so
6.38
times 10 to the sixth plus 3.5
times 10 to the 6
will give us an r value
of 9.88
times ten to the six
and let's not forget to square
so the gravitational acceleration
is greatly reduced now it's 4.08
meters per second squared
so the gravitational acceleration
greatly decreases
as you move away from the earth it's
still present but it's a lot weaker the
closer you get towards the earth the
greater the acceleration
so let's say at point c
the gravitational acceleration is going
to be a lot less
let's work on our last question
planet x has a gravitational
acceleration
of 7.5 meters per second squared
so that's the g value
and it has a radius
of 4.5 times 10 to the 6 meters
so what is the mass
of planet x
well let's start with this equation
lowercase g is equal to g m over r
squared
our goal
is to get m by itself
so i'm going to multiply both sides by r
squared over g
on the right side r squared will cancel
and g will cancel
so m is equal to this stuff
so the mass of the planet
is going to be the gravitational
acceleration
times the square of the radius divided
by the gravitational constant
so that's how we could find it
so it's going to be 7.5
meters per second squared
times the radius of 4.5 times 10 to the
sixth
squared
divided by
6.67 times 10 to the minus 11.
so the mass of this planet
is 2.28
times 10
to the 24 kilograms
so anytime you know the radius of the
planet
and the gravitational acceleration of
that planet you can actually calculate
the mass of the planet
you